<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
  ~ This is part of Geomajas, a GIS framework, http://www.geomajas.org/.
  ~
  ~ Copyright 2008-2013 Geosparc nv, http://www.geosparc.com/, Belgium.
  ~
  ~ The program is available in open source according to the GNU Affero
  ~ General Public License. All contributions in this program are covered
  ~ by the Geomajas Contributors License Agreement. For full licensing
  ~ details, see LICENSE.txt in the project root.
  -->
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.4/docbookx.dtd">
<chapter id="chapter-java-configuration">
  <title>Editing of Graphics Objects</title>

  <section>
    <title>The Graphics Controller System</title>

    <para>A number of functions can be attributed to a graphics object; this is done by registering controllers.
		If you click the created polygon or line, these controlers will become active. In the example below, the object
		can be resized (see the square handlers that make up a box around the object), dragged and also,
		there is a pencil image visible on the left hand top position. If you click this, you will go to the editing mode
		of the object. You can change the shape of the object by dragging the existing points or add/delete points.</para>
	  <screenshot>
		  <screeninfo>A line and polygon graphics object. The right one has been
			  selected.</screeninfo>

		  <mediaobject>
			  <imageobject>
				  <imagedata align="center" fileref="images/graphicsediting_controller_select.png" />
			  </imageobject>
		  </mediaobject>
	  </screenshot>

	  <screenshot>
		  <screeninfo>Clicking the pencil image puts the object in editing mode.</screeninfo>

		  <mediaobject>
			  <imageobject>
				  <imagedata align="center" fileref="images/graphicsediting_controller_edit.png" />
			  </imageobject>
		  </mediaobject>
	  </screenshot>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>The Graphics Action System</title>

    <para>The graphics project has a second way to register actions on an object. They are registered in a special controller.
		This controller will show up as a cog image on the top left position of the object's box, when you click the object.
		Clicking the cog shows a number of registered actions. Clicking <emphasis>Edit Shape</emphasis> brings the
    object again in an editing state. </para>
	  <para>The advantage of using the action system as supposed to the controller system for editing object, is
		  that more than one action can be registered at the same time. You see in the example below that
		  also actions <emphasis>Delete</emphasis> and <emphasis>Edit Style</emphasis> are active.</para>

    <screenshot>
      <screeninfo>Two polygon objects. The right one has been
      selected.</screeninfo>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata align="center" fileref="images/graphicsediting_action_select.png" />
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </screenshot>

    <screenshot>
      <screeninfo>Clicking the cog shows an action menu.</screeninfo>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata align="center" fileref="images/graphicsediting_action_menu.png" />
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </screenshot>

    <screenshot>
      <screeninfo>The polygon in the editing state.</screeninfo>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata align="center" fileref="images/graphicsediting_action_edit.png" />
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </screenshot>

    <para>More detailed information on the graphics action registration system
    is explained in the documentation of the Graphics Project. The content of
    the cog menu depends on the properties of the graphics object. The
    <emphasis>Edit Shape</emphasis> action will only appear if the object has
    a <code> GeometryEditable</code> role.</para>
  </section>
</chapter>
